I am going to be talking about secrets.
سأقوم بالحديث عن الأسرار
Obviously the best way to divulge a secret
من الواضح أن أحسن طريقة لإفشاء سر
is to tell someone to not say anything about it.
هي أن تخبر أحدهم أن لا يقول شيئا بخصوصه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Secrets. I'm using PowerPoint this year
أسرار. أنا أستخدم شرائح البوربوينت هذه السنة
just because, you know, I'm into the TED thing.
فقط لأنه، تعرفون، أنا من معجبي TED.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And when you use these things you don't have to go like that.
و حين تستعمل تلك الأشياء لا تكون مضطرا أن تفعل ذلك.
You just press it.
تضغط فقط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Oh, man. Um, yes.
يا رجل. امم، نعم.
Yes. I'm sure! Just change it!
نعم! أنا متأكد! فقط قم بتغييرها!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Is Bill Gates here?
هل بيل غيتس موجود؟
Change it! Come on! What?
غيرها! هيا! ماذا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Ah! Okay.
أه! أوكي.
That's not my slides, but it's okay.
هذه ليست شرائحي، لكن لا بأس.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As you can see, these are all maps.
كما ترون، كل هذه خرائط.
And maps are important devices for transferring information,
والخرائط هي أدوات مهمة في نقل المعلومات.
especially if you have human cognitive ability.
خصوصا إن كنت تملك قدرة الإنسان الإدراكية.
We can see that all formulas are really maps.
نستطيع رؤية أن كل الصيغ هي في الحقيقة خرائط.
Now, as humans, we make maps of places
الآن، كبشر، نرسم خرائط أماكن
that we seldom even go,
نادرا ما نذهب إليها.
which seems a little wasteful of time.
الذي يبدو شيئا ما مضيعة للوقت.
This, of course, is a map of the moon.
هذه، بالطبع، خريطة القمر.
There're some very delightful names.
هناك بعض الأسماء الممتعة.
Tranquilacalitis, [unclear]. My favorite is Frigoris.
ترانكويلاكيليتس، [غير واضح]. المفضل لدي هو "فريغوريس" (بمعنى برودة).
What are these people thinking? Frigoris?
ما الذي يظنه هؤلاء؟ "فريغوريس"؟
What the Frigoris you doing? Names are important.
ماذا تفعله بحق "الفريغوريس"؟ الأسماء مهمة.
Frigoris? This is the Moon. People could live there one day.
"فريغوريس"؟ هذا القمر. قد يعيش الناس هنا يوما ما.
I'll meet you at Frigoris. No. I don't think so.
سألتقيك في "فريغوريس". لا. لا أظن ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There we see Mars, again with various names.
هناك نرى المريخ، مرة أخرى مع أسماء شتى.
And this is all done, by the way,
وهذا كله تم القيام به، بالمناسبة
by the International Astronomical Union.
من طرف الإتحاد الفلكي الدولي.
This is an actual group of people
هناك فعلا جماعة من الأشخاص
that sit around naming planetary objects.
يقعدون ويسمون الكائنات الكوكبية.
This is from their actual book.
هذا من الكتاب الأصلي.
These are some of the names that they have chosen, ladies and gentlemen.
هذه بعض الأسماء التي اختاروها، سيداتي سادتي.
I'll go through a little of them. Bolotnitsa.
سأمر ببعضهم، "بولوتنيتسا".
That, of course, is the Slavic swamp mermaid.
تلك، بالطبع، حورية المستنقعات السلافية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now I think the whole concept of a mermaid
الآن أعتقد أن فكرة الحورية
doesn't really blend into the swamp feel.
لا تتماشى مع الصفة الخاصة للمستنقع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Oh look! Mermaid come out of swamp. Oh boy!
"أه أنظر! حورية تخرج من المستنقع. يا للمفاجأة!
It's time for Bolotnitsa!"
إنه وقت "البولوتنيستا!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Djabran Fluctus.
فلاكتوس دجابران.
If that don't flow off the tongue, what does?
إن كان ذلك لا يخلع اللسان، فما الذي يفعل؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean kids are studying this stuff
أقصد الأطفال يدرسون هذه الأشياء.
and they've got the word "fluctus" up there. That's wrong.
وقد وضعوا كلمة "فلاكتوس" هناك. هذا خطأ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
One dyslexic kid and he could be ruining his life.
طفل واحد عسير القراءة ويمكن أن يكون قد أفسد حياته.
"It fluctus up, Mama."
"ماما، إنها فلاكتوسية"
Hikuleo Fluctus.
فلاكتوس هيكليو.
That's a little more flowing. Hikuleo
هذا أكثر سلاسة قليلا. "هيكليو"
sounds like a kind of a Leonardo DiCaprio
يبدو كأنه نوع من ليوناردو دي كابريو
17 syllable thing.
17 مقطع لفظي.
And that's the Tonga underworld.
وذاك يعني عالم الرذيلة التونغاوي.
And one of my favorites is the Itoki Fluctus,
وواحد من أفضلها عندي هو فلاكتوس إيتوكي،
who is the Nicaraguan goddess of insects, stars, and planets.
من هي إلهة الحشرات والنجوم والكواكب النيكاراجوية.
Now, if you're a goddess of stars and planets
الآن، إن كنت إلهة الكواكب والنجوم
wouldn't you relegate insects to somebody else?
ألن تحيل الحشرات لشخص آخر؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"No, no, really, I'm so busy with the stars.
"لا، لا، حقا، أنا مشغول مع النجوم.
Would you mind taking the insects? Thank you darling.
هل لك أن تأخذ الحشرات؟ شكرا لك عزيزي.
Oh take the spiders too. I know they're not insects, but I don't care.
أوه خذ العناكب كذلك. أعرف أنها ليست حشرات، لكن لا أهتم.
Monkeys, chimps, just get rid of the hairy creatures."
القرود، الشيمبانزي، تخلص من الكائنات المشعرة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, we're going to be going to Mars one day. And when we do,
الآن، سوف نذهب إلى المريخ يوما ما. وحين نفعل
it's going to be unfair for the people that are living there
سيكون من الظلم للناس الذين سيعيشون هناك
to have to live with these ridiculous names.
أن يكونوا مرغمين على العيش مع تلك الأسماء السخيفة.
So, you'll be on Mars, and you're at
إذن، ستكون في المريخ، وأنت موجود في
Hellespointica Depressio
هيليسبوينتيكا الإكتئاب
which has got to be a really "up" place.
والذي يجب فعلا أن يكون مكانا "مرتفعا".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, I'm at the Depressio, and I want to get over to Amazonis
نعم، أنا في "الإكتئاب"، وأريد الذهاب إلى "أمازونيس"
so I plug it into the Mars map,
لذلك أوصله بخريطة المريخ،
and click the button and there's my directions.
وأضغط الزر وتلك هي إتجاهاتي.
I go to Chrysokeras.
أذهب إلى "كريسوكيراز".
(Laughter) Left to the Thymiamata.
(ضحك) يسارا نحو "التايمأماتا".
Then to Niliacus Lacus,
ثم نحو بحيرة "نيلياكوس"،
which is not a bad name.
وهو إسم ليس بالسيء.
Niliacus Lacus, try to get the practice, slick-a-tick-a-bacus.
بحيرة "نيلياكوس"، حاول أن تجرب، بقعة-قرادة-باكوس.
That's a cool name. I will say that.
ذاك إسم ممتاز. سأقول كذلك.
So, I hold back a little of my venom
إذن، سأكبح قليلا حقدي
for these astronomical misnomers.
على هؤلاه الأسماء الفلكية المغلوطة.
And then of course Arnon to Thoth.
ثم بالطبع "أرنون" نحو "ثوت".
And of course there will be advertisements.
وبالتأكيد سيكون هناك إعلانات.
This is from their rule book, the International Astronomical Union.
هذا من كتاب قواعدهم، الإتحاد الفلكي الدولي.
And you know they're international because
وتعرفون دوليتهم لأنهم
they put it "en Francais" as well.
كتبوها بالفرنسية كذلك.
L'Union Astronomique Internationale,
L'Union Astronomique International,
for those of you who don't speak French.
لمن لا يتحدث منكم الفرنسية.
I thought I'd translate for you.
فكرت أن أترجم لكم.
From the rulebook: Nomenclature is a tool.
من كتاب القواعد: التسمية وسيلة.
The first consideration, make it clear, simple and unambiguous.
أول اعتبار، جعلها واضحة وبسيطة وغير مبهمة.
And I think that Djabran Fluctus,
وأعتقد أن فلاكتوس "دجابران"،
that fits that mode.
أنه يلائم هذا النمط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's simple, the goddess of goats, very simple.
إنه بسيط، إلهة الماعز، بسيط جدا.
Djabran Fluctus.
فلاكتوس "دجابران".
"Now, Frank is this clear to you, Djabran Fluctus?"
"الآن، فرانك هل هذا واضح لك، فلاكتوس "دجابران"؟"
"Yeah, that's the goat goddess right? The Abacazanian?
"نعم، تلك إلهة الماعز أليس كذلك؟ الأباكازانية"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's clear to me."
ذلك واضح بالنسبة لي."
"Listen, I'm going back to the swamp mermaid. Can you call me in a little while?"
"اسمع، أنا راجع إلى حورية المستنقعات. أيمكن أن تتصل بي بعد وهلة؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Also, from the actual document
كذلك، من الوثيقة الأصلية
I highlighted a part I thought may be of interest.
أبرزت جزء فكرت أنه قد يكون مهما.
Anyone can suggest changing a name.
أي كان يمكنه أن يقترح تغيير إسم.
So, I look to you, fellow member of the Earth community.
لذلك، أتطلع إليكم، زملائي أعضاء المجتمع الأرضي.
We've got to change this stuff up fast.
علينا أن نغير هذه الأشياء بسرعة.
So, these are actual names of people that work there.
إذن، هذه الأسماء الحقيقية للأشخاص الذين يشتغلون هناك.
I did some more investigation.
قمت بالمزيد من التحقيقات.
These are more people working for this group.
هؤلاء أشخاص آخرون يعملون في المجموعة.
And, as you can see, they don't use their first names.
و، كما ترون، فإنهم لا يستعملون أسماءهم الشخصية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
These are people naming planets, and they won't use their first names.
هؤلاء أشخاص يسمون الكواكب، ولا يريدون إستعمال أسمائهم الشخصية.
Something is askew here.
هناك أمر لا يستقيم هنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Is it because his name is really Jupiter Blunck?
هل ذلك بسبب أن إسمه الحقيقي هو المشتري بلانك؟
Is that Ganymede Andromeda Burba?
وهل ذاك غانيميد أندروميندا بوربا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Is that Mars Ya Marov?
هل هذا المريخ يا ماروف؟
I don't know. But it's investigative material, no doubt.
لا أعرف. لكن هذه أمور تستدعي التحقيق، لا شك في ذلك.
There are some mapping people who do use their names.
هناك بعض راسمي الخرائط الذين يستعملون أسماءهم.
Witness please, Eugene Shoemaker,
شاهدوا رجاء، أوجين شوماكر،
who, diligently, from a young boy
والذي، بجد، منذ طفولته
decided he wanted to make maps of celestial bodies.
قرر أن يرسم خرائط للأجرام السماوية.
Must have been a very interesting day in the Shoemaker house.
لا بد وأنه كان يوما مهما في منزل شوماكر.
"Mom, I want to make maps."
"أمي، أريد أن أرسم الخرائط."
"That's wonderful Eugene. You could make maps of Toronto."
"ذاك رائع يا أوجين. يمكنك أن ترسم خرائط لتورنتو."
"No, I want to make maps of planets."
"لا، أريد أن أرسم خرائط كواكب."
"Yeah, go to your room."
"نعم، إذهب إلى غرفتك."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Martians, Venusians, Jovians.
مريخيون، أشخاص من الزهرة، أشخاص من المشتري.
We have names for places where people don't exist.
لدينا أسماء أماكن حيث لا يوجد أشخاص.
That seems a little silly to me.
هذا يبدو لي نوعا ما سخيفا.
There are no Jovians.
ليس هناك أشخاص في المشتري.
Getting back to my premise, I used stamps, by the way,
نعود إلى افتراضي الأساسي، بالمناسبة، قد استعملت الطوابع
because you don't have to pay anybody for the rights.
لأنه ليس عليك أن تدفع شيئا مقابل الحقوق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
There is obviously Einstein, Niels Bohr,
هناك بالتأكيد أينشتاين، نيل بوهر،
de Fermat's last theorem, and I'm not sure whether that's James Coburn
آخر نظرية لدي فرمات، ولست متأكدا هل هذا جيمس كوبورن
or Richard Harris.
أو ريتشارد هاريس.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's definitely one of the two. I'm not really clear which one.
هو بالتأكيد أحد الإثنين. لست متأكدا أيهما.
But obviously the point is that numbers are maps.
لكن واضح أن الفكرة هي أن الأرقام خرائط.
And within numbers, is there an underlying secret to the universe?
وضمن الأرقام، هل هناك سر كامن للكون؟
That is the premise of this particular presentation.
تلك الفرضية الأساسية لهذا العرض بذاته.
By the way, that's a natural picture of Saturn,
بالمناسبة، تلك صورة طبيعية لزحل،
no adjustments. I mean that's just beautiful.
دون تعديلات. أعني إنه لأمر جميل.
So beautiful that I will even give up a laugh
جميل جدا إلى درجة أنني سأتخلى عن ضحكة
to explain my love of this particular planet,
لأشرح مدى حبي لهذا الكوكب بذاته،
and the day Saturday, named after it, wonderfully.
ويوم السبت، سمي بسببه، بروعة.
So, formulas relate number to form.
إذن، الصيغ تربط العدد بالنموذج.
That's Euler, his formula
ذاك هو أولير، صيغته
was one of the inspirations that lead to the beginning of string theory
كانت إحدى الملهمات التي قادت إلى بداية نظرية الأوتار
which is kind of cool, not that funny, but it is cool.
والذي هو أمر رائع، ليس مضحكا، بل رائع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He was also famous for having no body.
كان كذلك معروفا بأنه بلا جسد.
Which a lot of you are like, "How did he figure that out?"
وكثير منكم سيقول، "كيف أمكنه أن يدرك ذلك؟"
He's got no body, no man, just a head floating high.
ليس لديه جسد، لا إنسان، فقط رأس يطفو عاليا.
Here comes Euler.
ها قد جاء أولير.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that's an icosahedron,
وذاك هو عشروني أوجه،
which is one of the five sacred solids, very important shapes.
والذي هو أحد خمس مواد صلبة مقدسة، أشكال مهمة جدا.
You see the icosahedron again.
ترون العشريني الوجوه ثانيا.
The dodecahedron, it's dual.
الإثني عشري السطوح، إنها مزدوجة.
There is a dodecahedron which I had to do in my room last night.
وذاك إثنا عشري سطوح كان علي إنجازه في غرفتي ليلة أمس.
The five sacred solids, as you can see there.
الأشكال الخمس المقدسة، كما يمكنكم أن تروا هناك.
Which is not to be confused with the five sacred salads.
والتي لا ينبغي الخلط بينها وبين السلطان الخمس المقدسة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Blue cheese, ranch, oil and vinegar, thousand islands and house.
جبن أزرق، مزرعة، زيت وخل، آلاف الجزر ومنزل.
I suggest the house.
أقترح المنزل.
The reality, now here is something important.
الحقيقة، الآن هناك شيء مهم.
What's important about this is
المهم بخصوص هذا هو
these shapes are duals of each other.
أن الأشكال ثنائيات مع بعضها البعض.
And you can see how the icosahedron
ويمكنكم رؤية كيف أن العشريني الأوجه
withdraws into the dodecahedron
يسحب في الإثنا عشري السطوح
and then they just merge into each other.
وثم يندمجان في بعضهما البعض.
So, the whole concept of branes in the universe,
لذلك، الفكرة الأساسية للبرينات في الكون،
if the universe is shaped like a dodecahedron
إذا كان الكون على شكل إثني عشر السطوح
this is a very good map of what could possibly be.
تلك خريطة جيدة لما يمكن أن يكون.
And that is, of course, what we are here to talk about.
وهذا، بالطبع، ما نحن هنا للحديث بخصوصه.
What a coincidence!
يا لها من مصادفة!
October 9th, in France, Jean-Pierre Luminet
التاسع من أكتوبر، في فرنسا، جان بيير لوميني
said that the universe is probably shaped like a dodecahedron,
قال بأنه من المحتمل أن الكون هو على شكل إثني عشر السطوح،
based on information that they got from this probe.
بالإعتماد على المعلومات المأخوذة من هذا البحث
This would be a normal wave pattern.
هذا من الممكن أن يكون نمط موجة.
But what they're seeing, way out there in the far reaches
لكن الذي يرونه، بعيدا في الأقاصي
of the microwave background,
من خلفية الميكروويف،
is this kind of odd undulation.
هو هذا النوع الغريب من التموج.
It doesn't plug in to what they suspected a flat universe would be.
لا يتوافق مع ما كانوا يظنون أن كونا مسطحا سيكون عليه.
So, you can kind of get an idea from this
لذلك، يمكنكم نوعا ما أن تستنتجوا فكرة من هذا
extrapolating that back under this huge picture,
نستقرئ هذا رجوعا إلى هذه الصورة الكبيرة،
so we get this idea of what the primal universe looked like.
لنكون فكرة حول شكل الكون البدائي.
And judging from this, it looks a little like a cheeseburger.
وبالحكم على هذا، يبدو شيئا ما وكأنه برجر بالجبن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, I'm thinking the universe is either a dodecahedron or a cheeseburger.
لذلك، أعتقد أن الكون إما إثنا عشر سطوح أو برجر بالجبنة.
And for me, that's a win-win.
وبالنسبة لي، فإن ذلك فوز-فوز.
Everybody goes, I'm happy.
الجميع يذهب فرحا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Better really hurry up.
يجدر بي فعلا أن أسرع.
I just threw this in because
رميت هذه هنا فقط لأنه
as important as all of our intellectual abilities are,
بقدر أهمية قدراتنا الفكرية،
without heart and without love it's just -- it's all meaningless.
بدون قلب وبدون حب هي فقط -- كل شيء بدون معنى.
And that, to me, is really beautiful.
وذلك، بالنسبة لي، حقا جميل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Except for that creepy guy in the background.
باستثناء ما يخص الشخص الغريب في الخلفية.
Getting back to the point of my particular presentation,
نعود إلى محور عرضي الخاص،
Kepler, one of my great heroes,
كيبلر، أحد أبطالي العظماء،
who realized that these five solids, which I spoke of earlier,
الذي أدرك أن تلك المواد الصلبة الخمسة التي تحدثت عنه قبلا،
were related somehow to the planets,
متصلة بطريقة ما بالكواكب،
but he couldn't prove it. It freaked him out.
لكنه لم يستطع إثبات ذلك. وذلك قد روعه.
But it did lead to Newton discovering gravity.
لكن ذلك قاد إلى اكتشاف نيوتن للجاذبية.
So, maps of things leading to organized understandings
لذلك، خرائط الأشياء تقود إلى تفكير منظم
of the universe in which we emerge.
للكون الذي نعيش فيه،
Now this is Isaac from a Vietnamese stamp.
الآن هذا إسحاق من طابع بريدي فيتنامي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I am not suggesting at all that my Vietnamese brothers and sisters
لست أقترح أن كل إخواني وأخواتي الفيتناميين قد
could maybe use a little art class here and there. But ...
يكونوا استخدموا القليل من الفن هنا وهناك. لكن..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
that's not a good picture.
تلك ليست صورة جيدة.
Not a good picture. Now, my friends in the island of Nevis
ليست صورة جيدة. الآن أصدقائي في جزيرة نيفيس
are a little better. Look at that! That's Isaac Newton.
هم أحسن بقليل. انظروا إلى ذلك! ذاك إسحاق نيوتن.
That guy is rockin'.
هذا الشخص نجم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What a handsome cat.
ياله من قط وسيم.
Once again, Nicaragua let me down.
مرة أخرى، نيكاراغوا، أتركني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And Copernicus looks like Johnny Carson, which is really weird.
وكوبرنيكوس يبدو مثل جوني كارسون، وهو أمر غريب.
I don't get that at all.
لا أستوعب ذلك على الإطلاق.
Once again, these guys rock it out.
مرة أخرى، هؤلاء الأشخاص يدفعونها للحد.
Isaac is kickin' ass. Man, he looks like a rock star.
إسحاق بالفعل رائع، يبدو كنجم روك.
This is freaky is a major way.
هذا مخيف لدرجة هائلة.
This is Sierra Leone.
هذه سيراليون.
They got little babies in there, floating in there.
هناك أطفال صغير هناك، يطوفون هناك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Man. I don't really need to comment on this.
يا رجل. لا أحتاج بالفعل أن أعلق على هذا.
But I didn't know that Isaac Newton was in the Moody Blues. Did you?
لكنني لم أكن أعرف أن إسحاق نيوتن كان من عشاق المودي بلوز. ماذا عنكم؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When did this happen?
متى حصل ذلك؟
It's a different kind of course. And they've got five apples?
إنه نوع مختلف بالطبع. ولديهم 5 تفاحات؟
I mean these guys are extrapolating in realms
أقصد هؤلاء الأشخاص يستقرؤون عوالم
that are not necessarily valid.
ليست بالضرورة صالحة.
Although five is a good number, of course.
على الرغم من أن 5 هو رقم جيد، بالطبع.
Ecuador, my friend Kepler,
إكوادور، صديقي كيبلر،
as you can see, they call him Juan.
كما يمكنكم أن تروا، سموه خوان.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Juan? No! Johannes, not Juan.
جوان؟ لا! خوان، ليس جوان.
It wasn't Carlos Chaplain. It's wrong.
لم يكن كارلوس شابلين. ذلك خطأ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
René Descartes, of course. Once again
ريني ديكارت، بالطبع. مرة أخرى
these Grenada people, this is like way too sick
هؤلاء الجريناديون، هذا مريض إلى درجة كبيرة
for anybody's imagination.
بالنسبة لمخيلة أي كان.
He's all murky. There is little kids leaning on his leg,
هو قاتم. هناك أطفال صغار يتكئون على ساقه،
little ghosts flying around. We gotta clean this stuff up
أشباح صغيرة تطير في المكان. علينا أن ننظف هذا
fast, ladies and gentlemen.
بسرعة، سيداتي سادتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is, of course, the Cartesian coordinates.
هذه، بالطبع، الإحداثيات الديكارتية.
Once again, that's Sierra Leone.
مرة أخرى، هذه سيراليون.
This is again, indicating how numbers
وهذا مجددا، يوضح كيف أن الأرقام
relate to space relate to form, maps of the universe.
مرتبطة بالفضاء مرتبطة بالشكل، خرائط الكون.
Because that's why we're here, really, I think to figure stuff out and to love each other.
لأن ذلك حقا هو سبب وجودنا هنا، أعتقد معرفة الأشياء وحب بعضنا البعض.
Descartes. (Laughter)
ديكارت. (ضحك)
Before the horse. (Laughter)
قبل الحصان. (ضحك)
Now, Monaco took Descartes, and just flipped him around.
الآن، موناكو أخذت ديكارت، وقامت بقبله أفقيا.
Now, Monaco is problematic for me, and I'll show you why.
الآن موناكو إشكالية بالنسبة لي، وسأريكم لماذا.
Here is a map. All they have is a casino on it.
هنا الخريطة. كل ما لديهم فيها هو كازينو.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And why Franklin Delano Roosevelt is on their map
ولماذا فرانكلين ديلانو روزفلت موجود في خريطتهم
I don't even want to hazard a guess.
لا أعرف ولا أريد حتى أن أغامر بالتخمين.
But I'd say he'd been to Hellespointica Depressio recently.
لكن يمكنني القول بأنه كان في هيليسبوينتيكا الإكتئاب مؤخرا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is the flag of Monaco. Ladies and gentlemen,
هذه راية موناكو. سيداتي سادتي،
the flag of Indonesia. Please examine.
راية إندونيسيا. فضلا تفحصوا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Not sure how this came to be, but it's not right.
لست متأكدا كيف حصل ذلك، لكنه ليس مناسبا.
In Monaco, "No, what are you talking about?
في موناكو، "لا، ما الذي تتحدث عنه؟
They are so different.
إنها مختلفة تماما.
Look, ours is more red, it's longer.
انظر، رايتنا أكثر احمرارا، إنها أطول.
They stole our flag! They stole our flag!"
لقد سرقوا رايتنا! لقد سرقوا رايتنا!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Bode's law wasn't even his law. It was a guy named Titus.
قانون بود لم يكن حتى قانونه. كان شخصا إسمه تايتوس.
And the reason I just bring this up because it is a law that doesn't really work.
والسبب الذي جعلني أذكر هذا هو أنه قانون لا يشتغل حقا.
That's Jude Law and some of his films recently didn't work.
هذا "جود لاو" وبعض أفلامه مؤخرا لم تنجح.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Just a correlation that indicates how things are misinterpreted.
فقط ارتباط يدل على أن الأشياء يساء تفسيرها.
And I wonder if the photographer said, "Okay, Jude,
وأنا أستغرب إن كان المصور قد قال، "أوكي جود
could you touch your tooth? That's good."
هل يمكنك أن تلمس سنك؟ هذا ممتاز."
Just a tip, if you're being photographed
مجرد إرشاد، إن كان يتم تصويركم
for press pictures, don't touch your teeth.
من أجل الصحافة مثلا، لا تلمسوا أسنانكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Prime numbers, Gauss, one of my favorites.
الأرقام الأولية، غاوس، أحد المفضلين لدي.
Golden section, I've been obsessed with this thing
القسم الذهبي، لطالما كنت مهووسا بهذا
since before I was born.
قبل أن أولد حتى.
I know that scares a lot of you,
أعرف أن هذا يفزع الكثير منكم،
but that was my purpose entirely.
لكن ذاك كان الغرض الأساسي.
There we can see Fibonacci numbers related to the Golden Section,
هناك يمكننا رؤية أرقام فيبوناتشي مرتبطة بالقسم الذهبي،
because Fibonacci and Golden Section
لأن فيبوناتشي والقسم الذهبي
relate to the unfolding of the measured meter of matter, as I refer to it.
مرتبطة بالكشف عن قياس متر من الماتر، كما أعبر عنه.
If Fibonacci had been on Paxil,
إن كان فيبوناتشي كان يتعاطى الباكسيل،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
that would be the Fibonacci series.
تلك ستكون متتالية فيبوناتشي.
"Ten milligram, 20 milligram."
"10 ميليغرام، 20 ميليغرام."
"Leonardo, dinner's ready, put down those books and take your pills."
"ليوناردو، العشاء جاهز، ضع جانبا تلك الكتب وتناول حبوبك."
"Yes, Mama."
"حاضر، أمي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Alright where is this going? That's a good question.
طيب إلى أين أنا ذاهب بهذا؟ هذا سؤال جيد.
Here is the premise that I began 27 years ago.
ها هو الإفتراض الذي بدأت 27 سنة خلت.
If numbers can express
إن كان الأرقام تعبر عن
the laws of this incredible universe that we live,
قوانين هذا الكون البديع الذي نعيش فيه،
I reason, through some sort of reverse engineering,
برهنت، عن طريق نوع من الهندسة العكسية أنه
we could extrapolate from them
في الإمكان أن نستقرئ منها
some basic structural element of this universe.
بعض الأمور البنيوية الأساسية في هذا الكون.
And that's what I did. Twenty-seven years ago
وهذا ما فعلته. منذ 27 سنة
I started working on this.
بدأت العمل على هذا.
And I tried to build a particle accelerator.
وجربت أن أبني مسرع جسيمات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that didn't work out well.
وذلك لم ينجح كذلك.
So, then I thought a calculator is a metaphor.
إذن، فكرت أن الآلة الحاسبة هي مجاز.
I can just divide numbers, that's like atom smashing.
يمكنني أن أقسم الأرقام، ذاك مثل تحطيم الذرة.
That's what I did. That's how I found Moleeds.
وهذا ما فعلته. هكذا وجدت "الموليدات".
Moleeds are what I believe
الموليدات هي ما أعتقد أنه
the thing that will allow string theory to be proved.
الشيء الذي سيتيح أن يتم إثبات نظرية الأوتار.
They are the nodes on the string,
إنها العقد في الأوتار،
patterns and relationships, 27, 37.
الأنماط والعلاقات، 27، 37.
That was the first chart I came up with.
هذا كان أول رسم بياني وضعته.
You can see, even if you don't go for the numbers,
يمكنكم أن تروا، حتى إن لم تهتموا بالأرقام،
the beauty of the symmetry.
جمال التماثل.
The numbers from one to 36, divided into six groups.
الأرقام من 1 إلى 36، مقسمة إلى 6 مجموعات.
Symmetry, pairs.
تماثل، أزواج.
Every top adds up to 37.
مجموع القمم هو 37.
Bottom, all 74.
القيم الدنيا، كلها 47.
There is so many intricate relationships that I'm not going to go there now,
هناك الكثير من العلاقات المعقدة والتي لن أذكرها الآن،
because you would say, "Hey, go back to the Fluctus part."
لأنكم ستقولون، "مهلا، عد إلى الجزء المتعلق بالفلاكتوس"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Circle of Fifths, acoustic harmony, geometric symmetry.
دائرة الأخماس، الانسجام الصوتي، التناظر الهندسي.
I knew those two were related.
كنت أعرف أن هذين الإثنين مرتبطان.
Once again, the Cartesian kind of cross-over.
مرة أخرى، الديكارتية نوعا ما.
So, I said if I'm going to put a circle,
لذلك، قلت إن كنت سأضع دائرة،
see what kind of patterns I get, boom, the Red System.
لأرى أي نوع من الأنماط سأحصّل، بوم، النظام الأحمر.
Look at that. You can't just make this stuff up, ladies and gentlemen.
أنظر إلى ذلك. لا يمكنك أن تختلق شيئا كهذا، سيداتي سادتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You can't just go around going, "Oh, I'm going to put some triangles in a circle
لا يمكنك فقط أن تأتي وتقول، "أوه، سأضع بعض المثلثات في دائرة
and they're going to be symmetrical. And they're all going to add up,
وسوف تكون متماثلة. وسوف تضاف على بعضها،
and it's going to be, oh yeah, I figured that out."
ثم تصبح، أوه نعم، لقد اكتشفته."
This is beyond anything anybody could just make up.
هذا أمر يفوق ما قد يختلقه فقط أي كان.
There is the Orange System.
إنه "النظام البرتقالي".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you'll see over here, these are multiples of the number 27.
وسوف ترون هنا، كل هذه مضاعفات للرقم 27.
And they recapitulate that shape,
وهي تلخص الشكل،
even though that's a circle of nine and that's a circle of 36. It's nuts.
بالرغم من أن تلك دائرة 9 وتلك دائرة 36. إنه جنون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's the Green System. It all folds in half
ذاك هو النظام الأخضر. كلها تطوى في النصف.
on the Green System, right between 18 and 19.
في النظام الأخضر، بين 18 و19.
The Blue System. The Violet. It's all there.
النظام الأزرق. النظام البنفسجي. كلها هناك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Look at that! I mean you cannot make that stuff up.
انظروا إلى ذلك! أقصد لا يمكنك فقط أن تختلق ذلك.
That just doesn't fall out of a tree, ladies and gentlemen.
هذا لا يسقط ببساطة من الشجرة، سيداتي سادتي.
Twenty-seven years of my life!
27 سنة من حياتي!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'm presenting it here at TED. Why?
وأها أعرضها هنا في TED. لماذا؟
Because this is the place if aliens land, I hope they come here.
لأن هذا هو المكان الذي إن جاءت الكائنات الفضائية، أتمنى أن تأتي إليه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"We are going to destroy the Earth. Hmmm ... maybe not."
"سوف نخرب الأرض. اممم .. أو لا"
In this last year I have found these subsequent systems
في السنة الماضية وجدت هذه الأنظمة التابعة
which allow for the mathematic possibilities
والتي تتيح لإمكانيات رياضيات
of the Calabi-Yau manifolds
فتحات كالابي-ياو
in a way that doesn't necessitate these little hidden dimensions.
بطريقة لا تستلزم هذه الأبعاد الصغيرة المخفية.
Which works mathematically, but it just doesn't seem God-like to me.
والذي يصلح رياضيا، لكنه لا يبدو عملا عملا إلهيا بالنسبة لي.
It just seems like it's not sexy and elegant, it's hidden.
يبدو فقط أنه ليس جذابا وأنيقا، إنه مخفي.
I don't want hidden, I want to see it.
لا أريد المخفي، أريد رؤيته.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I found other pairs all have symmetry,
وجدت أزواجا أخرى كلها لها تماثلية،
even though, unlike the master one, their symmetry is split.
على الرغم من أنها على خلاف الرئيسية، تماثليتهم مقسمة.
Unbelievable. This is like crazy.
غير معقول. هذا أمر مثل الجنون.
Am I the only one that sees this?
هل أنا الوحيد الذي يرى هذا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, I didn't just draw this in a day, by the way.
تعرفون، لم أرسم هذا في يوم واحد فقط، بالمناسبة.
You know, try making some charts like this at home.
تعرفون، حاولوا أن ترسموا مثل هذه المخططات في بيوتكم.
You gotta be accurate! There's measurement involved, increments.
عليك أن تكون دقيقا! هناك حسابات ينبغي إعتبارها وزيادات.
These are maps, by the way.
هذه خرائط، بالمناسبة.
Not stamps, but one day.
ليست طوابع بريدية، لكن في أحد الأيام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Okay, I'm getting to the punch. Golden Ratio, it's crazy.
حسنا، أصل الآن إلى اللكمة. النسبة الذهبية، إنه جنون.
And look at this, built within it is the Golden Ratio.
وانظرو إلى هذا، المبني بالداخل هو النسبة الذهبية.
I start looking at that, and look at them again.
بدأت أنظر إلى ذالك، ونظرت مجددا.
They start looking like planets.
صارت تبدو كأنها كواكب.
I go to JPL.
أذهب إلى مختبر الدفع النفاث.
I look at the orbits of the planets.
أنظر إلى مسار الكواكب.
I find 18 examples of it in our solar system.
أجد 18 مثالا به في نظامنا الشمسي.
I never told anybody. This is the first thing. This could be history.
لم أخبر أحدا من قبل. هذه المرة الأولى. هذا قد يكون تاريخا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Kepler was right.
كيبلير كان محقا.
Eighteen and 19, the middle of the Moleeds, 0.618 is the golden section.
18 و19 متوسط الموليدات، 0.618 هو القسم الذهبي.
Multiply them together, 18.618 x 19.618 is 365.247.
اضربهم مجددا، 18.618 ضرب 19.618 هو 365.247.
Which is .005 different from the number of days in a year.
والذي هو مختلف ب0.05 عن عدد الأيام السنة.
Hey, you can't make this up.
مهلا، لا يمكنك إختلاق شيء كهذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.